Hello and good מועד, Moed, good 35th of the עומר. Omer. Today's
דף daf is דף מ"ו. Daf Mem Vav. We pick up in
the middle of מ"ה עמוד ב' Mem Hey Amud Bet and we
spent a lot of time yesterday dealing with a girl who is
a קטנה ketana who gets married on her own and then the
father comes into the picture somehow and there's a and then the
question is is there some concern of קידושין kiddushin or not? Did
the father want it or not want it? There's a question at
the end about what the מסקנא maskana of the גמרא Gemara is,
although most ראשונים Rishonim פוסקן pasken that we don't have any concerns
there, no need for גט, get, no need for מיאון miun and
so on. Now, the גמרא Gemara deals with a case where the
father was aware of it from the very outset. So let's take
a look. Middle of מ"ה עמוד ב'. Mem Hey Amud Bet. נתקדשה
לדעת אביה. Niskadsheh lada'as aviha. She got married, this קטנה, ketana, with
her father's knowledge. Maybe he even married her off or maybe she
married herself but it was clear the father was okay with it.
However that works, you know שליחות shlichus doesn't exactly work for קטנה,
ketana, but however that works anyway, the marriage was clear that that
was binding and the father was on board.
והלך אביה למדינת הים. Vehalach aviha limedinas hayam. And then the father
goes away to a distant country. ועמדה וניסת. Ve'amda venises. And then
they went straight to the חופה. chuppah. Okay, so how about when
the חופה chuppah is שלא לדעת אביה? shelo lada'as aviha? Do we
assume that since the קידושין kiddushin was לדעת אביה, lada'as aviha, he'd
be happy for the חופה chuppah whenever it took place or do
we assume that he's not okay with the חופה? chuppah? And it
also raises an interesting question, right? Which is like to what degree
is חופה chuppah type of a קנין kinyan that requires דעת? da'as?
Right, if somebody had you know, is it a normal way of
thinking about חופה chuppah is that the קידושין kiddushin sort of creates
the marriage sort of the you know in law and then it
but and then it becomes a matter of fact once they start
living together? And then it doesn't require as much of the normal
type of you know דעת da'as that goes into creating a new
קנין. kinyan. Nevertheless, נישואין nisuin let's not forget, so on one hand
you'd say maybe the דעת da'as of the father is not so
critical once they just start living together, they've just translated it from
a matter of law to a matter of fact. On the other
hand, let's not forget that נישואין nisuin is when she leaves the
father's control. While she's still אירוסין arusin and a קטנה ketana or
נערה naarah she's under the father's control. So basically it is, you
know even if in a normal case of an adult a נישואין
nisuin the level of דעת da'as required might not be the same
as a normal קנין. kinyan. Here one imagines that she cannot actually
transition out of the father's control into the husband's control without the
father's okay. So here there was a חופה, chuppah, he wasn't asked
but he was okay with the קידושין. kiddushin. Do we assume that
that creates a status of her being a נשואה nesua or not?
What does that mean? She has to leave her home, like what
does it mean?
No well we'll see the נפקא מינות. nafka minas. Let's take a
look at some נפקא מינות. nafka minas. One immediate one is eating
תרומה terumah if she's a כהן. kohen. Another נפקא מינה nafka mina
is is that if she dies does her husband inherit her? There's
a lot of נפקא מינות nafka minas about her being a נשואה.
nesua. All the financial נפקא מינות nafka minas kick in when there's
קידושין kiddushin and נישואין. nisuin. Yes.
I just want, maybe this is obvious, just want a really clear
image. When it says ועמדה וניסת amda venises we do not mean
they're standing under a canopy and saying שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot.
Well we might, I mean.
But this language means like you've said, right, she gets up and
she goes, she's carried into her husband's house.
Well not carried but no I mean I mean the גמרא Gemara
talks about you know there's חופה chuppah and there's what the גמרא
Gemara calls נישואין ממש. nisuin mamash. Right נישואין ממש nisuin mamash probably
refers to the fact that yes they've begun living together. But you
know but yes there's also the חופה chuppah which is sort of
like the ritual that creates נישואין. nisuin. I mean the גמרא Gemara
in one place distinguishes it from נישואין ממש. nisuin mamash. So it
could be that as well. Could be there was a חופה. chuppah.
Yeah but I mean חופה chuppah is sort of the ritual that
effects the נישואין. nisuin. So it is not exactly clear but one
of those, right? I mean yes ניסת nises probably most simply means
they started to start living together. Yeah okay. So now let's continue.
So it says what's the story? אמר רב אוכלת בתרומה עד שיבוא
אביה וימחה. Amar Rav ocheles biterumah ad sheyavo aviha veyimcheh. That
she's presumed to be a נשואה nesua and she can eat תרומה
terumah if her husband's a כהן kohen which you can't until you're
a נשואה nesua until the father comes and the father protests. Meaning
not that we know that that'll happen, if the father protests then
retroactively she won't have been a נשואה. nesua. Okay it's not clear.
I mean it is good quest like once she becomes an adult
presumably then even if the father isn't good with it she's now
making that decision now. But presumably if still she's a קטנה ketana
and a נערה naarah the father can protest.
So the kids wouldn't be then. What? What are you gonna say
like let's say she has kids out of wedlock? Yeah, that's what
I'm saying.
That doesn't matter and it's not out of wedlock, whatever, there's no
halakhic status to that. What? Yes, that's what Michael said, there's no
problem. They're not they're not if she's not another man's wife she's
not not married to him. There is קידושין. kiddushin. Okay so that's
not the issue. The basic issue the difference between being a נשואה
nesua and not a נשואה nesua are all the reciprocal financial obligations
that a husband has to a wife. And תרומה terumah is one
area of like more of a ritual נפקא מינה nafka mina but
other things like the nature of the kids the nature of the
sex that's like less you know relevant. I mean there is true
you know there's a whole גמרא Gemara about ארוסה בעל ארוסתו בבית
חמיו arusah ba'al arusato beveit chamiv etc. but. That's less directly relevant.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says—I mean, yes, after קידושין Kiddushin before נישואין Nisuin they're not supposed
to be having sex, and some ראשונים Rishonim understand that it's actually
like, you know, that like there's an actual like איסור דרבנן issur
d'Rabbanan for them to be having sex between קידושין Kiddushin and נישואין.
Nisuin. But but, you know, that's not as much of a—like whether
they're transgressing that איסור issur or not is not the bigger question
here. The bigger question is like the practical נפקא מינות: nafka minas:
can she eat תרומה, Terumah, you know, what's the story with the
ירושה Yerusha and so on?
Okay. Right.
So, okay. So he says that she's presumed to be נשואה nesua
if it comes—the father protests, probably whilst she's still a קטנה ketana
or נערה, na'ara, then retroactively she wasn't a נשואה. nesua. Was she
doing an עבירה aveira or not? We'll see about that. But the
presumption is the father is okay with it.
Okay. Okay, רב אסי אמר אינה אוכלת—no, Rav Assi amar eina ocheles
she can't eat, שמא יבוא אביה וימחה—because shema yavo aviha v'yimcheh we're
assumed that he might protest, and therefore we can't presume that he's
okay with it. So do we start with a presumption that he'll
probably be okay with it? ונמצא זר אוכל בתרומה למפרע—and v'nimtza zar
ochel b'Terumah l'mafre'a if he does protest, retroactively she'll be a non-כהן's
Kohen wife, you know, not
the—and eating תרומה, Terumah, or not a נשואה nesua to a כהן
Kohen eating תרומה. Terumah. Okay, הוה עובדא וחש לה רב להא דרב
אסי—there hava uvda v'chash lah Rav l'ha d'Rav Assi was a story
and רב Rav was concerned with the position of רב אסי Rav
Assi and said that we shouldn't have her eat תרומה Terumah yet.
Okay. Now the way
וחש לה, v'chash lah, some ראשונים Rishonim say he didn't really פסק
pasken like רב אסי, Rav Assi, he was just being מחמיר machmir
like רב אסי. Rav Assi. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, שאם מתה—now, she'im mesa the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
רב Amar Rav: שמואל Shmuel בר רב Rav יצחק—רב concedes—I'm sorry, because
רב Rav himself, not just some ראשונים, Rishonim, excuse me, רב Rav
himself was the one who said that מן הדין min hadin she's
allowed to eat תרומה. Terumah. Nevertheless, in a practical case, he was
being מחמיר machmir like the position of רב אסי. Rav Assi. So
as a matter of law, he said she could eat תרומה; Terumah;
practically, he was being מחמיר machmir like רב אסי. Rav Assi.
Does she want to eat תרומה Terumah anyway?
Well, only מדאורייתא, mide'oraisa, not מדרבנן, miderabbanan, and which is what we're
going to get to.
אמר רב שמואל בר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak
ומודה רב—רב concedes—שאם מתה אינה יורשה—that she'im mesa eina yorshah if she
were to die, he would not inherit her. Even though רב Rav
considers her enough his wife that she can eat תרומה, Terumah, or
the נשואה nesua that she can eat תרומה, Terumah, it's not considered
definitive enough that there's נישואין nisuin for the aspects of ירושה. yerusha.
The husband only inherits the wife after נישואין. nisuin. Why? אוקי ממונא
בחזקת מריה. oki mamona b'chezkas mareih. Okay, because you establish the money
in the possession of the original owner. You don't know whether there
is נישואין nisuin for sure or not, and therefore you don't take
the property out of her control and give it to him if
she dies, because it's not black and white, it might be that
she's not נשואה. nesua. Now obviously the question is that if רב's
Rav willing to concede enough that there's a ספק safek of whether
she's married or not so that he won't transfer the property if
she dies, how does he let her eat—I mean, or that she's
נשואה—how nesua does he let her eat תרומה? Terumah? And here basically
רש"י Rashi and others point out, you know, תוספות Tosafot etc., that
at least according to the בבלי, Bavli, מדאורייתא mide'oraisa from the time
of קידושין Kiddushin the wife of a כהן Kohen can eat תרומה.
Terumah. She doesn't have to be a נשואה. nesua. The requirement of
נישואין nisuin is only a מדרבנן miderabbanan requirement. So at the end
of the day, רב Rav and רב אסי Rav Assi both agree
that her status as נשואה nesua is a ספק, safek, okay, but
רב—but Rav when it comes to the דרבנן d'Rabbanan issue of only
a נשואה nesua can eat תרומה, Terumah, רב Rav is willing to
be lenient. Okay, so that's the way at least רש"י Rashi and
תוספות—yes.
Tosafot So I'm trying to understand רב אסי, Rav Assi, 'cause I
mean the whole reason I thought it was מדרבנן miderabbanan is not
because an ארוסה arusa can't eat it, it's more worry that she's
going to like bring it back and this and this, right? But
but then to say because of that, you know, and the father
would have been good with this, I mean I
still don't—more's more.
Yeah, so תוספות Tosafot asks that—and תוספות Tosafot basically says that according
to רב אסי, Rav Assi, even if there's a ספק safek if
she's נשואה, nesua, the practical reasons we made the גזירה gzeira don't
really apply here because she's living with the guy. All right, so
תוספות Tosafot says אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, it's more or
less a לא פלוג. lo plug. Okay, so that's correct, yeah. Um,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
where are we?
Now,
נתקדשה לדעת ונישאת שלא לדעת. nitkadsha l'da'at v'nisas shelo l'da'at. Okay, now
let's say it's not that the father's in מדינת הים. medinas hayam.
The father married her off or he was okay with it, and
then there was the חופה, chuppah, and the father is here. Okay,
but did she elope? She sneaked behind his back and she eloped.
But the father's around. ואביה כאן—and v'aviha kan the father is like
right here. Okay. So what's the story? רב הונא אמר אינה אוכלת—no,
Rav Huna amar eina ocheles then she obviously can't eat. רב ירמיה
בר אבא אמר אוכלת—she Rav Yirmeya bar Abba amar ocheles can eat.
Now how does this make sense? And how does this tie into
the previous debate? Let's take a look. רב הונא אמר אינה אוכלת—she
Rav Huna amar eina ocheles can't eat
תרומה—דאפילו לרב דאמר אוכלת—even when רב Rav says she can eat when
the father is in a far away country, התם הוא דלא איתיה
לאב—there hasam hu d'lo isei l'av the father isn't around, so we
can presume that he'll be okay with it when he finds out.
אבל הכא דאיתיה לאב—here aval hacha d'isei l'av there's a father. Now
finally we get to find out, what was the father's reaction? So
the reaction is—is that there was no reaction. She did it, she
eloped behind his back, and when the father found out, presumably—apparently—he said
nothing. So we have to explain his silence, because if he said
'I'm okay with it', so he's okay with it. If he says
'I'm not okay with it', he's— not okay with it. So the
only question that's at stake here is that he's silent. Okay. So
when he's not around, we can presume he'll be okay with it.
But if he's around and he's silent, האי דאשתיק, hai de'ishtik, the
fact that he was silent, מרתח רתח, mirtzach ratach, he's just so
angry to say like to to say anything. You don't interpret his
silence as being okay. רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר אוכלת שיקני Rav
Yirmeya bar Abba amar ochelet shikani ואפילו רב אסי דאמר אינו אוכלת,
v'afilu Rav Assi d'amar ein ochelet, even רב אסי Rav Assi says
she can't eat when the father's in a distant country because we're
afraid he'll protest, התם הוא דשמא יבא אביה וימחה, hasam hu d'shema
yavo aviha v'yimche, that's because we're afraid that he'll protest when he
finds out. אבל הכא דאשתיק, aval hacha de'ishtik, here that he's silent,
אנוחי אנח ליה, isnuche ishnach leh, he's okay with it. Now of
course like it's very bizarre because if you start with the presumption
he'll be okay, presumably that should inform how you interpret his silence.
And if you start with a presumption that he probably won't be
okay, that will inform it. The only position that really makes sense
here to switch from the case of being far away and being
present and silent, I think, is the position of who was it?
The last one, רב ירמיה בר אבא, Rav Yirmeya bar Abba, because
there you could say, look,
absence of a reaction I'm afraid he'll protest. Hearing something and not
responding, like normally we have an idea שתיקה כהודאה, shtika k'hoda'ah, right?
If you heard something and you didn't respond, it means at least
you've made your peace with it. You might not be thrilled about
it, but we would normally presume that if you are opposed to
it, you would say something. So that can make sense, that normally
we're concerned he'll be opposed, but if he's silent and doesn't react,
that changes it. But to say the opposite direction I don't understand.
We presume he'll be okay, but if he heard about it and
didn't say anything, we assume he's so angry he can't say anything,
like that seems very strange. All right. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
It's what will people say? It's the people around are the concern.
Yes. Because, you know, presumably the people who are familiar with the
with the family
with the with the father will know whether he's angry.
Right, right, right. Right.
Maybe it's about, it's about what you know, what will people say?
What will they think?
How will it be interpreted? Right. Because he raised a good question,
like how can we make a general rule about what the silence
means rather than looking at each case and trying to interpret? Right.
Okay. That's a good point. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says, let's take a look. Now,
נתקדשה שלא לדעת אביה ונישאת שלא לדעת אביה ואביה כאן. niskadsha she'lo
l'da'at aviha v'nisat she'lo l'da'at aviha v'aviha kan. So now we're going
to get even a more extreme case. She—the whole thing was eloped.
She got married without telling her father, the קידושין, kiddushin, she did
the נישואין nisuin without telling her father. The father's here and presumably,
again, presumably once he finds out, he's silent. רב הונא אמר אוכלת,
Rav Huna amar ochelet, she can eat. רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר
אינו אוכלת, Rav Yirmeya bar Abba amar ein ochelet, she can't eat.
Now of course the bizarre position is she can eat. You have
two things going against her.
אמר עולא הא דרב הונא, amar Ulla hada d'Rav Huna, that that
רב הונא Rav Huna said that she can eat, כחומץ לשינים וכעשן
לעינים, k'chometz l'shinayim u'k'ashan l'einayim, is like, you know, is like vinegar
to the teeth and smoke to the eyes. It's like an intolerable
position. Because why?
So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא ומה התם דקדושי דאורייתא אמרת לא
אכלה, hashta u'mah hasam d'kiddushei d'oraita amart lo achla, when she was
definitely married and then it was just because רב הונא Rav Huna
said that even when it was
נתקדשה, niskadsha,
the קידושין kiddushin was לדעת אביה l'da'at aviha and the נישואין nisuin
was not and the father was around and silent—remember that was the
immediate previous case—רב הונא Rav Huna said we're afraid he's objecting, his
silence is objecting. So when the קידושין kiddushin was definitely good and
then he was silent about the נישואין, nisuin, we're afraid he's objecting
and we say לא אכלה. lo achla. הכא לא כל שכן, hacha
lo kol sheken, here when he wasn't even okay with the קידושין
kiddushin or he wasn't around for the קידושין, kiddushin, of course we
should assume that he's got a problem with it and that the
whole thing is no good. So the גמרא Gemara says, נירין דברי
תלמיד, nirin divrei talmid, so עולא—I Ulla mean עולא Ulla continues—says, you
know what, רב ירמיה, Rav Yirmeya, who was the תלמיד talmid of
רב הונא, Rav Huna, that makes a lot more sense. How could
רב הונא Rav Huna say that if he didn't object to either—if
he objected to only to the—if he was silent, excuse me, to
the latter—he was okay with the first and silent to the latter,
that's an objection. But if he was silent about both, then he's
okay with it? So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא, amar Rava, no, מאי טעמא דרב הונא?
mai ta'ama d'Rav Huna? הוא בנעשה במעשה יתום בחיי אב. ho'v'na'aseh b'ma'aseh
yatom b'chayei av. Because basically, this girl has been acting like she
has no father. Okay. Basically, what's been happening now, there are two
events, major events in her life, קידושין kiddushin and נישואין, nisuin, that
he hasn't reacted to. So in that case, the lack of reacting,
the fact that she's acting in sort of in disregard to the
fact that there's a father and the father isn't asserting his authority,
that basically, yes, even in that case we'll basically interpret it that
he's basically made his peace and decided he's let her make her
own decisions. He's okay with what she does. Okay. So when the
first act, the קידושין, kiddushin, was done under his control and auspices
and he had never like done anything to indicate he was relinquishing
his rights and control, and then the second act was שלא לדעת,
she'lo l'da'at, in that case we'll assume he's opposed even if he's
silent. But when he allows both things to happen and says nothing,
then we'll assume he's basically like, you know, just מתייאש. mitya'esh. Oh,
whatever, she's a strong-minded, independent-minded eleven-year-old, let her do whatever she wants.
Okay. So that's basically it. Now of course the interesting thing is
is that now at the end right we're back to this question
of question of a girl that does קידושין kiddushin שלא לדעת האב,
shelo l'da'as ha'av, does it actually become—how do we פסקן? pasken? When
the, does it actually become קידושין kiddushin or not? Here at least
this last opinion sounds like we would be concerned that it could
become קידושין. kiddushin. All right, so let's take a look now at
the last case in the גמרא. Gemara. איתמר: Itmar: קטנה שנתקדשה שלא
לדעת אביה. ketana sheniskadsha shelo l'da'as aviha. Back to that case, the
one that was our focus yesterday. אמר amar רב: Rav בין היא
ובין אביה יכולים למחות. bein hi uvein aviha yecholim limchos. Now remember,
you know, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both said that we're concerned,
excuse me, רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both said that she was
possibly מקודשת mekudeshes when it was שלא לדעת אביה shelo l'da'as aviha
and you know, required a גט get and a מיאון. miun. So
now the same רב Rav that says she's possibly מקודשת mekudeshes clarifies
and says that by the way, that was only until you heard,
you know, what we never clarified there is, well, what does the
father say? Remember we said she's possibly מקודשת mekudeshes שמא יתרצה האב.
shemen yisratzeh ha'av. But what
did the father say? So now we're clarifying that. And he's saying
oh, if when the father finds out about it he objects, okay,
then there's no concern of שמא יתרצה האב, shemen yisratzeh ha'av, then
clearly he's not okay with it and it's no good. All right.
Now, not only that, she can also object. Okay, now how can
she object? She accepted the קידושין kiddushin and who cares about her
objection? She's a minor. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says it's only if
she objects prior to the father finding out. Okay, so she accepted
the money, the father's going to find out tomorrow, and if he
objects tomorrow it's no good, but if he, before the father finds
out tomorrow, she objects, then that also makes it no good because
then before somehow it got validated by the father, you know, she
sort of cut it off, you know, before it could become, you
know, so somehow that undermines the acceptance of the money since she's
no longer okay with it. תוספות Tosafot says that she could possibly
even object even after the father says it's okay and the presumption
is that the father being approving of it is only assuming that
she's also okay with it. Of course that's strange because she was
okay with it initially and what is it, she has an indefinite
amount of time to object? So תוספות Tosafot is a little vague
on that point. But let's assume anyway that her objection either—let's assume
like רש"י Rashi makes it clear, תוספות Tosafot is vague—her objection occurs
before the father says he's okay. And therefore, either negates her act
of accepting the money or her father's acceptance is dependent on her
still being okay with it. Okay, so anyway but that's what we've
now introduced: that there's actually a time, until now we said we
presume she's, you know, according to רב, Rav, we're concerned the father's
okay. Now the father actually has a chance to respond. Okay, so
and if he says he objects, it's no good. Now, of course
that then raises the question: So what were we talking about until
now? If he says he's okay, he's ודאי vaday okay with it.
If he says he objects, it's no good. So what were we
talking about until now? What was all this debate about until now?
So תוספות Tosafot clarifies and look at תוספות: Tosafot: בין היא ובין
אביה יכולים לעכב. bein hi uvein aviha yecholim l'akeiv. תוספות Tosafot says
אף על גב דאמר רב לעיל חיישינן שמא יתרצה האב, af al
gav d'amar Rav l'eil chaishinan shemen yisratzeh ha'av, היינו בסתמא ששמע ושתק.
hainu b'stama sheshama v'shatak. Just like the סוגיא sugya we had before,
that until now we've been talking about the fact of how to
interpret his silence. Okay, ששמע ושתק. sheshama v'shatak. אבל היכא דמיחה גילה
בדעתו. aval heicha d'micha gila b'da'ato. Okay, but if he objected, that's
different. So based on this, we now, just like the previous סוגיא,
sugya, realize that the way תוספות Tosafot understands and a lot of
ראשונים, Rishonim, that the whole discussion before about this קטנה ketana that
got married and whether it's good or not is only in the
case that the father heard and initially was silent. And the question
is how to interpret that initial silence. But if he explicitly says
he's okay, it's good. If he explicitly says he objects, it's not
good. And not only that, she can object as well. Okay, so
that's a מיאון miun in קטנה. ketana. In other words, well, sort
of, yeah, right, yeah. But yes, but in a different way because
here there's a חשש קידושין דאורייתא chashash kiddushin d'Oraisa at least according
to רב. Rav. ורב אסי אמר אביה ולא היא: v'Rav Assi amar
aviha v'lo hi: only the father, which you know is the more
normal thing to say. אייתי רב הונא לרב אסי. Aysei Rav Huna
l'Rav Assi. So רב הונא Rav Huna asked רב אסי. Rav Assi.
ואמרי לה חייא בר רב לרב אסי. v'amri lah Chiyya bar Rav
l'Rav Assi. So now we're actually going to turn this whole case,
which we thought was a strange scenario and we were wondering how
often it would occur, he's going to actually turn it into a
case in the תורה. Torah. Okay, what's the case in the תורה?
Torah? אם מאן ימאן אביה לתתה לו. im ma'ein yema'ein aviha l'sitta
lo. Okay, this is about the case about the seducer and the
father refuses to go along with it, so he has to give
her, you know, 50 כסף, kesef, which is 200 זוז. zuz. Okay,
now, אין לי אלא אביה: ein li ela aviha: it's only we
only know the father can refuse. היא עצמה מניין: hi atzma minayin:
how we know she can refuse? תלמוד לומר אם מאן ימאן, Talmud
lomar im ma'ein yema'ein, מכל מקום, micol makom, double language. Now why
is that a question? Because he is presuming that the case in
the תורה Torah that she was seduced was not just he was
seduced that he should sleep with this guy. But the guy seduced
her to marry him and that the, and them having sex together
was an act of קידושי ביאה. kiddushei biah. And now the case
in the תורה Torah is exactly the case we've been dealing with
for the last two days. They slept together, okay, instead of giving
her a ring, they had sex, okay, but basically it was a
קטנה ketana or a נערה. na'arah. that had קידושין שלא לדעת אביה,
kiddushin shelo ldaas aviha, okay, and now the father finds out, and
the תורה Torah is telling us that the father can refuse, and
not only that, she can refuse based on the מדרש midrash that
she can also refuse. So that's exactly our case, except it's a
נערה, naara, it's not a קטנה, ketana, whatever. But anyway, it was
a קידושין kiddushin and when the father finds out, he can refuse
and the מדרש הלכה midrash halacha tells us she can refuse as
well. Okay, so don't you see from that that she can refuse?
אמר ליה רב לא תיזיל בתר איפכא. Amar lei Rav lo teizil
basar ipcha. Look,
don't look for problems. Don't go ahead and make like, turn things
around. יכולני לשינויי לך לכולא, Yacholni lshinuyei lach lchula, I can answer
you, כגון שפיתה שלא לשום אישות. kegon shepita shelo lshum ishus.
Now, I can answer you is funny because I think we all
probably presumed that was the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. Okay,
he was just interested in sex. He was seducing her not in
the context of marriage. Okay, so the case in the תורה Torah
where the father is objecting is not to prevent the קידושין kiddushin
from taking place. There was no קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says, פיתה שלא לשום אישות
קרא בעי? pita shelo lshum ishus kra baei? But what do you
need a פסוק pasuk for? If there was no act of קידושין,
kiddushin, of course the father can object to his daughter marrying this
guy. Since when shouldn't he be able to object to his daughter
marrying this guy? Like, the father's in control of who his daughter
can marry. So why does the תורה Torah have to tell you
that? So the answer is, it doesn't tell, exactly, it's not telling
you to tell you that she can't be forced to marry this
guy against the will of the father. That is obvious. The question
is, what is the consequence of them not getting married? The consequence
is, he has to pay חמישים כסף. chamishim kesef. So אמר רב
פפא בר יצחק, Amar Rav Pappa bar Yitzchak,
לומר שמשלם קנס כמפותה. lomar shemshalem knas kimefuta. No, to tell you
that he pays up the money. So yes, the פסוק pasuk is
not talking about an act of קידושין. kiddushin. It's talking that they
just had sex and it's telling you if the father objects, which
of course he's entitled to to the marriage, then the guy has
to pay a קנס. knas. אמר ליה רב אשי, Amar lei Rav
Ashi, אי הכי היינו דתנינא, ei hachi hainu dtanyana, מהר ימהרנה לו
לאשה, שצריכה הימנו קידושין. maher yimarena lo l'isha shetricha heimenu kiddushin. The
language מהר ימהרנה לו לאשה, maher yimarena lo l'isha, right, means that
now he has to, if the father doesn't object, the פסוק pasuk
says now he has to marry her. Now, there's an interesting question
what מהר ימהרנה maher yimarena means because מוהר mohar is normally understood
as the bridal price, right? Now, actually some have suggested that the
מסורתי masoretic reading of that פסוק pasuk is מהר ימהרנה לו לאשה,
maher yimarena lo l'isha, right, which is using מוהר mohar as a
verb. He should מוהר mohor her as a wife. Which, by the
way, shows that the מוהר mohar is a bridal price, right? There's
a whole question what מוהר mohar is, but especially if you read
the פסוק pasuk that way, it sounds very much that it is
the money that effects the קידושין. kiddushin. However, some have suggested a
non-מסורתי masoretic reading of that פסוק pasuk would be מהר ימהרנה לו
לאשה, mahor yimrena lo l'isha, he should quickly marry her. Okay, but
even if that were true, it probably still is a play on
the word of מוהר. mohar. Anyway, the פשט pshat of the פסוקים
psukim are telling you that it means, because you could, if you
would have said the other way, that the seduction was לשום אישות,
lshum ishus, then maybe all the פסוק pasuk is saying is that
he has to write her a כתובה ksuva or something, you know?
But anyway, we read מהר ימהרנה לו לאשה maher yimarena lo l'isha,
means marry her, which makes it clear that they haven't done an
act of קידושין kiddushin yet. Okay, and which is what he says.
You know what? You say that the seduction was not about marriage,
you're right. That tells you מהר ימהרנה לו לאשה maher yimarena lo
l'isha שצריכה הימנו קידושין. shetricha heimenu kiddushin. So that, so that's a
good read. So now the גמרא Gemara says, but isn't, isn't אי
הכי? ei hachi? Isn't that a question? No, some of the תוספות,
Tosafos, particularly רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, sometimes says that as a way
of saying, ah, now it makes sense, not as a question. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says now, ואי פיתה לשום אישות קידושין למה
לי? ve'ei pita lshum ishus kiddushin lama li? So now the גמרא
Gemara says okay, one minute, let's go back to the other read.
The other read of the פסוק pasuk is that the seduction was
for the sake of marriage and the father was objecting to the
קידושין. kiddushin. So if the father doesn't object to the קידושין, kiddushin,
why is the פסוק pasuk saying מהר ימהרנה לו לאשה? maher yimarena
lo l'isha? So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, צריכה קידושין לדעת
אביה. tricha kiddushin ldaas aviha. To tell you, you should do another
קידושין kiddushin now with the father's approval from the get-go. Which is
very strange, right? If you read the פסוק pasuk that he seduced
her לשום אישות lshum ishus and the father didn't object, what's מהר
ימהרנה לו לאשה maher yimarena lo l'isha saying? To do another קידושין?
kiddushin? Why do another קידושין? kiddushin? To do it properly? Do it
official now, now let's do it in the right way or something.
It's strange. Anyway, but there's another very interesting question here which is,
what does her objection mean? Okay, so listen to, we said the
scenario is the seduction was not לשום אישות. lshum ishus. The father
can object and he pays חמישים כסף. chamishim kesef. If they get
married, then the guy doesn't pay the חמישים כסף, chamishim kesef, right?
He only pays the חמישים כסף chamishim kesef if the father objects
because that's instead of the fact that she won't be getting a
כתובה ksuva etc. so that's going to presumably be hard for her
to get married. Okay,
so now, one minute though. Where's her objection? If she objects, she
can prevent the marriage from taking place? Maybe. But doesn't that, wouldn't
that be absurd? The father wants her to marry this guy, this
guy wants her to marry and all of a sudden this קטנה
ketana or נערה naara objects? Normally she has no say-so. All of
a sudden because she was seduced,
she can now say she doesn't want to marry the
guy? Right? What's going on? So if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos says like this, so he says כרבי. K'rabbi.
Okay,
so in this תוספות Tosfos כבר בעא Kvar Baye about halfway down,
the line starts with the word קנס. Knas. Okay, he says: משום
קנס דמפתה m'shum knas d'mifute פירוש peirush לעולם איכא פיתוי שלא עושה
אישות l'olam iysa pita she'lo osah ishus אפילו הכי אשמעינן רבותא afilu
hachi ashmi'unan ribusa דכי מעכבא איהי, d'chi m'akev ihi, when she objects,
שמשלם קנס she'mshallem knas דכמו דתלה הכתוב קנס דמפתה במיאון האב, d'k'mo
d'talah hakasuv knas d'mifute b'miun ha'av, the same way when he objects
he pays, כך תלו במיאון דידה. kach talo b'miun didah. Okay, והאי
מיאון דידה, v'hai miun didah, her objection, ודאי אינו מועיל לענין שלא
תנשא לו, vadai eino mo'il l'inyan she'lo tinaseh lo,
doesn't prevent her from getting married, דכיון דאביה רוצה שתהא אשתו d'keivan
d'avia rotzeh she'tehei ishto אינה יכולה
לעכב, eino yachola l'akeiv, if the father wants to marry her off,
since when can she say no? אלא מה המיאון שמשלם קנס כאילו
אב ממאן, ella mah hamiun she'mshallem knas ke'ilu av me'aein,
but it gets- it forces the guy to pay the קנס. knas.
Okay, and it goes to the father.
But then it's so absurd!
Then she- then the father takes her aside and says, 'Listen here
honey, here's what we're going to do. I'm going to be okay
with it, and then you're going to be ממאנת, m'mayer, so that
way you both get married and you get the קנס,' knas, right?
So that's very bizarre, that her objection should have the power to
make him pay the קנס knas even though she's getting married. He
still has to write her a כתובה. kesubah. He still has to
write her a כתובה. kesubah. Yeah. Anyway, תוספות's Tosfos second answer is
better. אי נמי נפקא מינה היכא דבעא Inami nafkaminei heicha d'ba ואחר
כך נתיתמה, v'achar kach nis'yas'ma, if the father died. That- that's when
her refusal works, okay? דהשתא מהני מיאון דידה לעכב שלא תהא אשתו.
d'hashta mehani miun didah l'akeiv she'lo tehei ishto. That's when her refusal
works. But it is a strange point that never gets really explored.
Once חז״ל Chazal say she can refuse, refuse what? Refuse the marriage?
Since when is she entitled to refuse the marriage if there's a
father around and she's still a קטנה ketana or נערה? na'arah? Okay?
So תוספות Tosfos has two answers. One is that the father isn't
around and the other is a strange idea that even if she's
getting married, he could still wind up paying the 50 כסף. 50
kesef. All right, that was the end of that סוגיא sugya about
getting married לדעת אביה שלא לדעת אביה l'da'as avia shelo l'da'as avia
and so on. And now we turn to our משנה, mishnah, back
to a case with- not the case of the minor which has
all those interesting dynamics, but a normal case of an adult woman
entering into קידושין. kiddushin. Yes? Didn't we say in contemporary times the
woman could object? So at what point- What do you mean contemporary
times? When- when did it change? You said, you know, that she
had no choice in the matter. Well, if she's a קטנה ketana
or a נערה. na'arah. Right. As long as there's a father around.
Did that ever change? No. As a קטנה ketana or נערה na'arah
if there's a
father around, yeah. Yeah, exactly. No, I think what I might have
said at one time is that in the פסוקים, psukim, the פסוקים
psukim don't even clearly limit it to her being- the פסוקים psukim
don't clearly identify an age when she's no longer under her father's
control. Now it could just be that the פסוקים psukim are taking
for granted that by the time she's in the- you know, some
time during the time she's a נערה, na'arah, her father's going to
get her married off. But the idea that there's an age called
בוגרת bogeres where she leaves her father's control just because of her
physical maturity and her age is not clear in the פסוקים. psukim.
She's a יבמה yevama that she doesn't have a choice. Right. Right,
right. So when רב Rav said בין היא ובין אביה יכולים לעכב,
bein hi u'vein avia yecholin l'akeiv, right? So- so she really- so
it just means לעכב l'akeiv in terms of getting a קנס? knas?
That's the first way תוספות Tosfos explains. The second way is better.
Okay, next משנה. mishna. Now back to a normal dynamic with an
adult woman about קידושין. kiddushin. האומר לאשה התקדשי לי, Ha'omer l'isha hiskadshi
li, and we saw this quoted yesterday, התקדשי לי בתמרה זו, hiskadshi
li b'tmara zo, התקדשי לי בזו, hiskadshi li b'zo, marry me with
this date, with this date. Okay, אם יש באחת מהן שוה פרוטה
מקודשת. im yesh b'achas meihen shaveh prutah m'kudeshes. So if one of
them was worth a פרוטה prutah she's married, ואם לאו אינה מקודשת,
v'im lav einah m'kudeshes, if not she's not, even if all of
them together are, because since he said, 'marry me with each date
that he gave,' 'marry me with this date, marry me with this
date,' whatever, then each one is a separate act and the dates
don't combine to be a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. Okay, if he
said- he gave- that was a good one. I was thinking about
the date pun but I hadn't- I hadn't gotten as far as
you. Okay. A cheap date. All right. בזו ובזו ובזו, B'zo u'v'zo
u'v'zo, now if he said 'marry me with this and this and
this,' okay, and he didn't say 'marry me' between each one, אם
יש שוה פרוטה בכולם מקודשת, im yesh shaveh prutah b'kulam m'kudeshes, ואם
לאו אינה מקודשת, v'im lav einah m'kudeshes, then as long as combined
they were worth a פרוטה prutah she's married. הייתה אוכלת ראשונה ראשונה,
Haysa ocheles rishona rishona, let's say she was eating each date as
he put it in front of her. אינה מקודשת עד שתהא באחת
מהן שוה פרוטה. einah m'kudeshes ad she'tehei b'achas meihen shaveh prutah. Then
it doesn't work that they combine to have a שוה פרוטה; shaveh
prutah; one by itself has to be a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah.
Why exactly that's true is going to be the focus of the
גמרא, Gemara, but first we just deal with a line we said
before, מאן תנא התקדשי התקדשי, man tana hiskadshi hiskadshi, who is the
תנא tana that says that until he- until she says- until he
says התקדשי, hiskadshi, the statements are seen as one collective statement and
the only way they're broken up into different acts is because he
repeated the word התקדשי, hiskadshi, you know, between each one. אמר רבה
רבי שמעון היא דאמר עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. amar Rabbah
Rabbi Shimon hi d'amar ad she'yomar shvuah l'chol echad v'echad. We had
this yesterday that if somebody says 'a שבועה shvuah I don't owe
you and a שבועה shvuah I don't owe you and a שבועה
shvuah I don't owe you,' those are separate שבועות shvuos and separate
קרבנות korbanos if he's lying, but if he says 'a שבועה shvuah
I don't owe you or you or you or you,' that's all
one. one big שבועה. shvua. So here too that same רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would say that if you say this date and this
and this and this and this, it's one act of קידושין. kiddushin.
It only becomes a separate act when you say marry me between
each one. Marry me with this, marry me with this, etcetera. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara continues, we had that yesterday. בזו ובזו
ובזו יש בכולן. Bezo uvezo uvezo yesh bekulan. Now we get to
this last line which is if she's eating it, then one of
them has to have a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. So the גמרא
Gemara says אהיי, Ahai, which part of the משנה Mishnah is that
going on? The first one where he breaks up the statements or
the last one where he combines them? Okay אי נימא ארישא, Ei
neima areisha, he says marry me with this, marry me with this,
מאי איריא אוכלת, mai irya ocheles, why is it only a scenario
when she's eating the dates that one of them has to have
a שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah by itself? אפילו מונחת נמי, Afilu munachas
nami, even if he just left them in front of her, דהא
התקדשי לי בזו קאמר. deha hiskadshi li bezo ka'amar. He said with
each separate date, marry me with this, so one of them has
to have a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. It's irrelevant that she's eating
them. We already okay that's the first case. So presumably אלא אסיפא,
ella aseifa, presumably it's going on the last case, that's what it
sounds like. ואפילו בקמייתא, Va'afilu be'kamyata, so what does this mean? It
means that he's saying marry me with this and she eats it,
and this and she eats it, and this and this and this.
So it's saying if one of them has a פרוטה prutah it
works. Okay presumably you can't have the collective having a פרוטה prutah
because by the end of his statement, if he said and this
and this and this and this and he threw five, by the
end he meant all of them together, and by the end of
the statement right four of them have already been eaten. Alright so
it's not enough that they combined have a פרוטה prutah because the
act of קידושין kiddushin is only over when he gives her the
fifth one and then the other ones aren't around. Okay but then
the גמרא Gemara says but then why did it work when the
first one had a פרוטה? prutah? Okay ואפילו בקמייתא va'afilu bekamyata so
in that case it would work if the first date had a
פרוטה. prutah. ומלוה היא, U'milveh hi, it's a loan. What does that
mean it's a loan? It means that the גמרא's Gemara going to
have a discussion in a minute. If a man says to a
woman marry me with like whatever this ring or this 20 bucks
and she takes the money then for some reason it turns out
that the קידושין kiddushin wasn't good. There was you know he made
some mistake, there was some condition it wasn't met, etcetera. Does he
have to give the money back? Okay this happens all the time
right, if a couple breaks up is she supposed to give back
you know the engagement ring? Does he have to give the does
she have to give the כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin back? So the
presumption of the גמרא Gemara is yes. So money given as כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin that doesn't wind up being כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin
is a loan and would have to be given back. So here
she is, she's eating these dates as he's putting them in front
of her. If it turns out that this is not going to
be a קידושין, kiddushin, okay, then she's going to have to give
it back. So right now that money is doesn't exist, it's not
in front of her, but it would be money theoretically that she
would owe him. Okay and then he says to me and then
so then we says well if that was a שוה פרוטה shaveh
prutah in the first one she's מקודשת. mekudeshes. So the גמרא Gemara
says well why? The first one isn't around anymore. If he just
said marry me with this and he stopped his statement and she
ate it, of course she'd be מקודשת. mekudeshes. He gave her a
פרוטה, prutah, she was okay, end of story. But what the גמרא's
Gemara saying is the act isn't over until the end, until he
gives her the fifth date. At that stage, okay, if the only
thing that was worth a פרוטה prutah was that first date and
he's saying marry me with that first date because by the marry
sort of the end of the act comes you know 10 seconds
later, then that first date doesn't exist right now, it's only money
that she has to give him back. So when he says keep
it you know just keep that money that you owe me and
marry me with and I'll marry you with that, then that's marrying
her with something that's not concrete, that's not around in front of
us, that's called מקדש במלוה mekadesh b'milveh and that doesn't work. Okay
so it's a little confusing why the גמרא Gemara exactly makes that
comparison but the basic point is is that the act of קידושין
kiddushin if it doesn't complete until he's done giving all five dates
and at that stage the other dates don't exist, then how does
it work that they were worth a פרוטה, prutah, who cares right
at that stage they don't exist and he's marrying her with a
debt and therefore that shouldn't work. Okay so hopefully this'll get clarified
as the גמרא Gemara responds, so let's take a look. ומלוה היא?
U'milveh hi? So אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan הרי שולחן והרי
בשר והרי סכין ואין לנו לאכול. harei shulchan veharei basar veharei sakin
ve'ein lanu leechol. We've got the table and the meat and the
knife and we can't eat, which is basically like everything seems so
clear and we don't have any way of explaining this משנה. Mishnah.
It seems like a very straightforward משנה Mishnah but you can't explain
this last line whether it's going on the beginning of the משנה
Mishnah or the end of the משנה, Mishnah, either way it doesn't
make any sense. It's like water, water everywhere, not a drop to
drink. Okay source of the expression the first date. Oh you're not
we're not going to hear the end of it. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay first date was a cheap
date. Anyway so רב ושמואל אמרי תרוייהו, Rav u'Shmuel amri tarvaihu, so
רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both say לעולם ארישא. le'olam areisha. It's
going on the first case where even where where any date by
itself like when he says התקדשי לי בזו hiskadshi li bezo התקדשי
לי בזו hiskadshi li bezo התקדשי לי בזו. hiskadshi li bezo. If
any one has a פרוטה prutah it works. So what's the point
of mentioning that she ate it? It would work even if, you
know, obviously it worked. It worked as soon as he gave her
the date. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא מבעיא קאמר, V'lo mibaya
ka'amar, goes without saying. לא מבעיא מונחת Lo mibaya munachat דאיכא שוה
פרוטה אין אי לא לא, d'ika shaveh prutah in ee lo lo,
of course if she's leaving the date in front of her and
there's a שוה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, of course it works and if
not it doesn't work, אבל אוכלת, aval ochelet, I might think that
if she's eating the date, הואיל ומיקרבא הנאתה, ho'il u'mekarva hana'atah, since
she immediately derives benefit from it, אימא גמרה ומקניא נפשה, eima gamra
u'maknya nafsha, maybe even if it was less than a פרוטה, prutah,
maybe she's basically saying for me this is worth a פרוטה. prutah.
The fact that she's showing that eagerness and eating it, maybe you
don't even need a פרוטה. prutah. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan
that you do. Now that's a very like weak חידוש chidush as
תוספות Tosafot points out, since when can she get to decide oh
for me this is worth a פרוטה? prutah? Right, we had an
earlier סוגיא sugya in the גמרא Gemara that made it clear that
it has to be an objective value of a פרוטה, prutah, but
nevertheless, that's the... they basically neutralize the last line of the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, even if she's eating the dates, it still needs to
be a פרוטה. prutah. Fine. Now we get to a more interesting
answer. רבי אמי אמר לעולם אסיפא. Rabbi Ami amar l'olam asseifa. It's
going on the סיפא seifa which is clearly פשט, pshat, okay. ומהי
עד שיהא באחת מהן שוה פרוטה? U'mai ad sheye'hei b'achat mehen shaveh
prutah? What does it mean as long as one of them is
worth a פרוטה prutah it works even if she's eating it, okay?
And that was remember a big collective, okay? עד שיהא באחרונה שוה
פרוטה. Ad sheye'hei b'achrona shaveh prutah. It doesn't mean any one of
the dates can be a פרוטה, prutah, although that's certainly what it
sounds like. It means that the last date has to be worth
a פרוטה. prutah. Okay, so here basically what's happening is let's understand.
He's saying this, this, this, this, and this. The act isn't done
until the end. If by the time the act is done, the
first four dates don't exist, then he can't marry her with those
dates, they don't exist anymore, they're just an outstanding מלוה. milveh. So
but if the last date has a פרוטה, prutah, and none of
those dates by them right, but if the last date has a
פרוטה, prutah, then when that's when he's done with his statement, and
this, period, then before she eats it, he's now given her something
worth a פרוטה prutah that she took, and therefore in that case
that works. Okay, so the sentence wasn't over until the end, and
by that stage the other stuff didn't exist anymore. He couldn't marry
her with it, even if the collective was worth a פרוטה prutah
or individually it was worth a פרוטה. prutah. But when he gives
her the last one and finishes his sentence, then before she gets
a chance to eat it, she accepts that last one, that works.
That's the קידושין. kiddushin. אמר רבא שמע מינה מדרבי אמי תלת. Amar
Rava shma mina mi'd'Rabbi Ami tlat. From this way that רבי אמי
Rabbi Ami explains the משנה, Mishnah, we can infer three things. שמע
מינה המקדש במלוה אינה מקודשת. Shma mina hamkadesh b'milveh einah mekudeshet. Number
one is, since he didn't challenge our question about this משנה, Mishnah,
we see that the early dates don't work because they're only a
מלוה milveh by the time the sentence is over. So therefore if
you marry with a מלוה milveh it doesn't work, which is going
to be a focus of upcoming of גמרא Gemara for a while.
ושמע מינה המקדש במלוה ופרוטה דעתה אפורטה. U'shma mina hamkadesh b'milveh u'prutah
da'atah a'prutah. Let's say somebody says I want to marry you with
the hundred dollars you owe me, you can keep that hundred dollars,
and here's a penny. Okay, does that work? So we could say
well maybe it doesn't work because he said with both of them,
and the מלוה milveh part doesn't work for the קידושין, kiddushin, so
the penny won't work for the קידושין kiddushin either, right? Or we
could say no, in that case since the מלוה milveh part isn't
relevant, doesn't work, that gets bracketed out. And the fact that both
he and she presumably, here the גמרא Gemara says דעתה, da'atah, another
גמרא Gemara actually says דעתיה, da'ateih, so in a way it
has to be both he and she have to be basically focusing
on the concrete פרוטה prutah in front of them, it does work.
Right, so in this case, right, he gives her a date and
a date and a date and a date, and she eats it.
All of these dates become a מלוה, milveh, and then this one
date is left as a פרוטה, prutah, right, and that's when he's
done with his sentence, okay? Right, this is he says ובזו, u'v'zo,
period. That's when he's done with his sentence. Like he says ובזו
ובזו, u'v'zo u'v'zo, right, ובזו ובזו. u'v'zo u'v'zo. This is when he's
done with his sentence. At this stage all of these are מלוה
milveh and this is the פרוטה prutah in front of her. But
he said marry me with all of this, right? His sentence was
ובזו ובזו ובזו ובזו. u'v'zo u'v'zo u'v'zo u'v'zo. So he's מקדש במלוה
ובפרוטה. mekadesh b'milveh u'v'prutah. Okay, so we might let's say it's not
good because maybe she only agreed to be married with everything combined,
and therefore, and this isn't good for כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Okay,
so we say oh no, if you try to marry with everything
combined, if there is a פרוטה prutah in front of you, then
we say that is, even though you said all of it, no,
everybody is focused on the פרוטה prutah and that becomes the act
of קידושין. kiddushin. דעתה אפורטה. da'atah a'prutah. What? דעתה אפורטה. da'atah a'prutah.
דעתה אפורטה. da'atah a'prutah. Okay. What? Yeah, but but before she gets
a chance to eat it, he put it in her hand, so
she was מקודשת mekudeshet before she ate it. Because he said if
there was only the first date, not this case but the previous
case, if only the first date was worth a פרוטה prutah and
this was not... Yeah, then it would be a מלוה, milveh, then
it would not work. If she was married, right? Oh when he
said התקדשי לי בזו, hitkadshi li b'zo, התקדשי לי בזו, hitkadshi li
b'zo, when he was... Okay, but if but regardless of how much
these were worth, if this one was worth a פרוטה, peruta, the
last one, then it does work. Wait, let me do the third
one. שמע מינה, Shema mina, and the third thing we infer from
this is מעות בעלמא חוזרים. Maot be'alma chozrin. The money normally, the
fact that we're calling this a מלווה, milva, this stuff, means that
if the קידושין kiddushin didn't go through, she'd have to pay it
back. Okay, because if we didn't call it a מלווה, milva, because
the very fact that we're calling it a מלווה. milva. Now תוספות
Tosafot asks one minute, but all that was you ask the question
isn't it a מלווה, milva, sort of like you know you're making
an assumption and then you're reading your assumption back out of you
know your conclusion. Says what's the alternative? The alternative would be that
even if the קידושין kiddushin didn't go through, let's say this one
last last one didn't have a פרוטה, peruta, the קידושין kiddushin didn't
go through, she'd be able to keep this, right? You can keep
the engagement ring it's okay. You can keep the money given for
קידושין kiddushin even if the קידושין kiddushin doesn't go through. That would
be מעות מתנה Maot matana as opposed to מעות מלווה. Maot milva.
Would that change the הלכה halacha of this case? Okay, so would
that change the הלכה? halacha? She's giving, she's eating eating eating eating,
says זו זו זו זו, zu zu zu zu, here he finishes
his sentence. So now the dates that she ate, what are their
status? Either their status is if this thing doesn't go through I'll
have to give it back, or whether it goes through or not
I get to keep it. How would that matter in terms of
how you understood whether this case would work? So תוספות Tosafot says
yes, it would matter. If this stuff was a מתנה matana and
not a מלווה, milva, then either way she basically is going to
keep it. Like take זו זו זו זו, zu zu zu zu,
whatever happens whether it winds up being a קידושין kiddushin or not
she gets to keep it. So תוספות Tosafot says if she's going
to get to keep it, okay, then תוספות Tosafot says in that
case we would be more prepared to say that even though the
stuff isn't בבעין, be'ein, it's all like you know it's all כסף
קידושין. kesef kiddushin. You could reframe the whole thing, you don't have
to look at it as well this doesn't exist that's money שחוב
shechov and that's מקדש במלווה. mekadesh be'milva. No, because in the case
that she gets keep it either way when you're giving it to
her whether it's going to turn out to be כסף קידושין kesef
kiddushin or not כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin she owns this date now.
So she's just eating a date that she owns. You give her
the next date, she's eating a date that she owns. Why should
we reframe this now as saying that it can no longer be
part of the קידושין? kiddushin? Either way she gets to keep it.
So therefore what תוספות Tosafot says is is that in that case,
okay, but then it still wouldn't explain the משנה, Mishnah, because then
the last one wouldn't have to be worth a פרוטה. peruta. If
all of this was if this all she got to keep whether
it wound up being מתנה matana or whether it wound up being
כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, then we would look at it all as
one act and we would say as long as combined they have
a פרוטה peruta it would be enough. Okay, so the only way
to explain the משנה Mishnah that one of them has to be
worth a פרוטה peruta by itself is through this idea of מקדש
במלווה. mekadesh be'milva. That's all a bit complicated but basically we define
this as money that might have to go back to him, so
it's a מלווה, milva, so it's separate conceptually from the קידושין. kiddushin.
It doesn't it wouldn't matter you know whether one of them had
a פרוטה peruta or not since by the time the sentence was
over it was owed money. And therefore only the last one, it'd
only work if the last one has a פרוטה. peruta. But if
we say that the money she gets to keep regardless, then it
might be fine if all combined it has a פרוטה peruta because
then it's all seen as like one big act, it's not we
don't separate the stuff she got at the beginning from the stuff
at the end. Yes. So whether this is a פשט pshat of
the משנה Mishnah or not, the גמרא's Gemara understanding that the point
of this משנה Mishnah legally is to explore the nature of קידושין
kiddushin as a קניין kinyan and to draw out the concept of
קידושין במלווה. kiddushin be'milva. That's another way... Well, not clear the גמרא
Gemara understands that, that's not clearly the גמרא's Gemara agenda on this
on this משנה. Mishnah. Right, right, that for the קניין kinyan to
be חל, chal, you he has to own what's presented to her.
Right, I mean that's the question is is that the money given
as כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin it doesn't always factor normal types of
you know sometimes it's more narrow, sometimes it's more broad than normal
questions about giving money, like we had a case we mentioned before
by the קטנה ketannah like throw the money in the ים, yam,
put the money on on a rock, you know might work, you
know which obviously you know מקדש במלווה mekadesh be'milva doesn't work. So
it has its own parameters. But yes, that's exactly what we're trying
to figure out what's the nature of the exchange that effects קידושין.
kiddushin. Okay, איתמר. itmar. Now we're going to do something which is
a little easier because this clearly is getting exactly why this matters
if it's מלווה milva or מתנה matana is a little confusing, but
anyway, here we get to a case that's you know fun and
a little bit more straightforward. המקדש אחותו, Ha'mekadesh achoto, a man marries
his sister. He goes to his sister and says הרי את מקודשת
לי בטבעת זו, Harey at mekudeshes li be'tabaat zu, okay, which obviously
didn't work. So does she have to give the ring back? Okay,
similar to our previous question. Okay, so רבא Rava אמר מעות חוזרים,
Maot chozrin, she has to give the ring back. ושמואל אמר מעות
מתנה. Ushmuel amar mos matana. No, the ring was a gift. Okay.
רב אמר מעות חוזרין. Rav amar mos chozrin. אדם יודע שאין קידושין
תופסין באחותו. Adam yodeya she'ein kiddushin topsin b'achoso. He knew obviously it
wasn't a good קידושין. kiddushin. וגמר ונתן לשום פקדון. V'gamar v'nasan l'shum
pikadon. So how do we interpret what happened? We'll interpret it as,
you know, hold onto this ring for me. So the גמרא Gemara
asks, ולימא לו לשום פקדון? v'leima lo l'shum pikadon? So say, hold
onto this ring for me. סבר לא מקבלה. Savar lo mikabla. Yeah,
she won't want to do it. But this way, it'll be, I
don't know, she'll think I'm marrying her or whatever or we'll just,
you know, it's a way I get the ring into her hand
sort of like serving papers and then she's winding up holding the
ring for me. But שמואל סבר מעות מתנה. Shmuel savar mos matana.
It's a gift. אדם יודע שאין קידושין תופסין באחותו. Adam yodeya she'ein
kiddushin topsin b'achoso. He obviously knew it wasn't going to take effect.
וגמר ונתן לשום מתנה. V'gamar v'nasan l'shum matana. So he gave it
to her as a gift. ונימא לו לשום מתנה? V'neima lo l'shum
matana? Say it's a gift. סבר כסיפא לה מילתא. Savar ksifa lei
milsa. No, it's embarrassing. So she or it'll be embarrassing for her.
She doesn't want to receive a gift. So it'll be better if
we do it as a pretense like we're getting married and then
she winds up sort of like, you know, keeping it. She doesn't
have to give it back. That's like the joke I tell, I
think I've told you before. This guy goes to someone and says,
hey, I'll sell you the Brooklyn Bridge. Says, really? How much? Just
a million dollars. So million dollars, great. So he takes out his
checkbook. He says, you got a pen? So the guy gives him
a pen. He signs the check, hands him the check, walks away.
So his friend says to him, he says, I don't understand what
you just did. He says, you just bought a bridge you don't,
you know, he didn't own with money you don't have. So the
guy says, what, and this pen is nothing? So alright, whatever. Anyway,
so he winds up, they did a whole little fake little act,
yet he winds up with a ring out of the end. That's
the way he gets what? כסיפא לה. Ksifa lei. כסיפא לה כסף.
Ksifa lei kesef. Anyway, fine. Alright, anyway. So מתיבי רבינא. Metivei Ravina.
So Ravina asked. Now of course, you know, the question is are
we really trying to get what's in their דעת, da'as, or are
we asking a different question which is is that, you know, just
legally how do we define that case? Like clearly if something was
given and there was in error, the money would go back. But
when it wasn't in error, everybody knew it didn't work and the
money exchanged hands, we have to define how do we look at
the nature of that transaction? Do we actually look like he actually
gave the thing as a gift or not? Okay, the easier thing
is to say it wasn't given as a gift. Right? The easier
thing is this was his object, what happened, how it was framed
was
not really what was happening, so then it didn't mean anything.
Give it back.
Okay, and שמואל Shmuel, is the
bigger חידוש chiddush
I think that it was a gift. Now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: what if you
assume that they know, everybody knows that there's no marriage here, so
why is he giving her the ring? Right, exactly. I don't know.
They're fooling around. You know, they're like, what would you do?
Do I mean, my point is that you would presume if the
thing wasn't real you would presume status quo, right? You would presume
rather than read a transaction into this act. That's my assumption. Like
so nothing legal happened.
If nothing legal happened then
the money didn't change ownership.
That's the way I would assume. Anyway, let's take a look. מתיבי
רבינא.
Metivei Ravina. Ravina asked. המפריש חלתו קמח. Hamfrish chalato kemach.
If somebody separates חלה challah while it's still dough, while it's still
flour. It doesn't take effect. חלה challah is only when it's dough.
Okay, אינו חלה. eino challah. It's not חלה. challah. וגזל ביד כהן.
V'gezel b'yad kohen. And if
the
guy gave the flour to the כהן, kohen, the כהן kohen can't
keep it.
And if he were to keep it he'd be stealing. So that's
similar. Gave a כהן kohen something that wasn't חלה, challah, presumably everybody
knew it wasn't חלה, challah, and we say the כהן kohen has
to give it back. He doesn't get to keep it.
ואמאי גזל ביד
כהן?
V'amai
gezel b'yad kohen?
According to שמואל, Shmuel why is it a theft? נימא אדם יודע
שאין מפרישין חלה קמח. Neima adam yodeya she'ein mafrishim challah kemach. Everybody
knows that you don't take חלה challah while it's still flour. ונתן
לשום מתנה. V'nasan l'shem matana. According to שמואל Shmuel say it's a
gift. Right? Same idea. If the transaction didn't mean anything
שמואל Shmuel, would
say well you'll make it into a gift. No, שאני התם דנפיק
חורבא מיניה. Shani hasam d'nafi churbah minei. If we say it's a
gift then that'll lead to a disaster. People will assume, if the
כהן kohen will
assume if he doesn't have to give it back, that means that
it
really is חלה. challah. And if it really is חלה challah then
what? זימנין דאית ליה לכהן פחות מחמש רבעי קמח. Zimnin d'is lei
l'kohen pachos m'chamesh rivayim kemach. He'll have less than the full amount
of flour that's חייב chayav in חלה. challah. Okay, it's five רבעי,
rivayim, we won't get into that, but he'll have just a little
bit less than the full amount. והאי V'hai and then he takes
the flour you gave him which he thinks is חלה challah and
he mixes it with the rest. Now the flour you gave him
is not חלה. challah. So because the actual objective reality is that
it's now obligated in חלה challah because he has a full amount
of flour but he'll think he's not obligated because he'll think a
little bit of this flour is already חלה challah so it doesn't
make the rest obligated in חלה. challah. Okay, וכסבר נתקנו סותה. v'kasavar
nitknu sosah. He'll think that his flour does not need to have
is okay. ואתי למיכל בטבל V'asi l'meichal b'tevel and he'll eat it
when it's טבל tevel because really the flour he added was not
חלה challah and therefore now the whole dough is חייב chayav in
חלה. challah. So the גמרא Gemara says that's why we have to
say give it back so he doesn't confuse it and think that
it's really חלה. challah. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. הא
אמרת אדם יודע שאין מפרישין חלה קמח. Ha amart adam yodeya she'ein
mafrishim challah kemach. Why would he confuse it? You said that everybody
knows that you don't give חלה challah when it's still flour. So
you're saying oh you've got to give it back or he'll think
it's really... People know the basic rule, you don't give חלה challah
while it's still flour, ואינו יודע, ve'eino yodea, but doesn't understand the
reason why. דסבר טעמא מאי, desavar ta'ama mai, why is it you
don't give חלה challah while it's still flour? משום טירחא דכהן, mishum
tircha dekohen, because you don't want to impose the burden on the
כהן kohen to turn the flour into dough. But they think that
maybe בדיעבד, bedi'avad, maybe it will work. They're not 100 percent sure
about the rules. They know you're not supposed to give it, but
they don't know what will happen if you do give it. So
if you then say the כהן kohen can keep it, right, then
they'll think that it actually did work בדיעבד. bedi'avad. Okay? וטירחא דכהן
אחיל ליה. vetircha dekohen achil lei. Okay, and the טירחא tircha on
the כהן, kohen, the כהן kohen is מוחל, mochel, he's willing to
accept it. So therefore you have to say give it back in
this case, so that because people's knowledge is a fluid thing, and
if you don't say give it back, that'll make people draw wrong
consequences about this. Okay, but normally you can keep it, if something
was given in a way that was understood that it didn't work.
So now the גמרא Gemara says דתהא תרומה ולא תאכל עד שיוציא
עליה חלה ממקום אחר. detehei terumah velo tochal ad sheyotzi alei challah
mimmakom acher. One minute. Why though does it work, vis-a-vis, why does
it say that it's not חלה? challah? If your concern is that,
hold on let me just double check here רש״י. Rashi. Right. Why
do you say he's got to give it back as a way
to tell him that it is not חלה, challah, right? Now we're
saying he really should be able to keep it. But if he
keeps it, he'll think it's חלה. challah. So force him to give
it back. The גמרא Gemara says we've got a better way to
tell him that it's not really חלה. challah. You're allowed to keep
it, but you have to be מפריש mafrish on it a second
time. This flour that this ישראל Yisrael gave you, you can keep
it. It was a מתנה. matanah. But you know what? It's not
really חלה. challah. And if you want to eat it, you
gotta be מפריש חלה mafrish challah on it.
Okay, so that's what it says. דתהא תרומה, detehei terumah, let it
be like תרומה, Terumah ולא תאכל עד שיוציא עליה חלה ממקום אחר.
velo tochal ad sheyotzi alei challah mimmakom acher. But you can't eat
from it until you're מפריש חלה mafrish challah on it. What does
that mean? מי לא תניא? mi lo tanya? We have a case
just like this. מן הנקוב על שאינו נקוב. min hanakuv al she'eino
nakuv. Somebody takes תרומה terumah, from a plant that grew with a
hole in it, a hole in the flower pot, on something that
grew without a hole in the flower pot. So the stuff without
the hole in the flower pot was not really biblically obligated in
תרומה. terumah So he took from some of his tomatoes that were
obligated in תרומה terumah. and he said this will be תרומה terumah
on all those hydroponic tomatoes, which weren't obligated. So the reality is
that this tomato isn't תרומה terumah and he's now going to give
it to a כהן. kohen. So what's the הלכה halacha we say
about this? תרומה, terumah so the כהן kohen who gets it treats
it as תרומה terumah, on the one hand, where מחמירין machmirin we
treat it as תרומה, terumah ולא תאכל עד שיוציא עליה תרומה ומעשר
ממקום אחר, velo tochal ad sheyotzi alei terumah uma'aser mimmakom acher, but
you can't eat it because it's not really תרומה, terumah, and you
can't eat until you're מפריש תרומה mafrish terumah on it again. So
sometimes we have these cases where something is mistakenly given that we
give it both statuses, תרומה terumah, and טבל. tevel. The כהן kohen
keeps it and he has to be מפריש mafrish again. So the
גמרא Gemara says so why by the flour did we not say
the same thing? Fundamentally according to שמואל, our orientation should be keep
the flour. Okay, your concern is that then they won't understand that
the flour is, they'll think the flour really is חלה challah and
it isn't, say fine, it's חלה challah and it's not חלה. challah.
It's חלה challah and you keep it and you have to be
מפריש mafrish again. So everybody understands that it's in this, that it's
not black and white what this status is. ממקום אחר mimmakom acher
means of an additional quantity, a portion from, right. רש״י Rashi points
out that in case there are cases you could take from the
thing itself, but yes, but it does mean yes, you add other
grain and you take from the whole thing. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so let's just read the answer. The גמרא Gemara says בתרי
מני ציית, בחד מנא לא ציית. bitrei many tzyat, bechad mana lo
tzyat. With two vessels they'll listen, one vessel they won't listen. What
does that mean? It means at some level they understand that there's
a difference between the hydroponic tomatoes and the normal tomatoes. So if
you tell him you can keep it but you have to be
מפריש mafrish again, they'll understand why I have to be מפריש mafrish
again. They'll understand the hydroponic tomatoes were a different story. But if
you tell him you can keep the flour, which is חד מנא,
chad mana, one vessel, okay, they won't understand. As long as I'm
keeping the flour, what you're really telling me is that it is
חלה. challah. So why do I have to be מפריש mafrish again?
So they more understand the problematics of the hydroponics case than they
do by the flour case. So by the flour case, the only
way where it's not going to be, you're not going to get
confused and you're not going to think that it really is חלה
challah is if
we demand that you return it. Okay, in the hydroponics case we
can let you keep it and you'll understand that there's still a
problem. But in the flour case, if we don't want you to
think that it's really okay, the only thing we can really say
is return it, otherwise we're afraid that you will get confused. Okay,
so anyway, so we'll end here and we'll continue with this issue
tomorrow. Okay, how do you stop this? Oh now you gotta. How
do you stop this?
Now you gotta I gotta unlock it in order to stop it.
Okay, so we are on דף כה *daf
chaf heh* עמוד א *amud aleph* at the bottom. We are discussing
the משנה *Mishnah* of מצא בכותל *matza b'kotel*. The משנה *Mishnah* says
that if you find it in a wall, if it is מחציו
ולחוץ *mechetzio velachutz*, it belongs to the מוצא *motzeh*. If it is
מחציו ולפנים *mechetzio velifnim*, it belongs to the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*.
The גמרא *Gemara* says, תנא *Tana*, when it is filled with חלודה
*chaludah*. If the coins are rusty, it means they are very old
and it is clear they are from the אמוריים *Emoriyim*. Therefore, even
if they are found מחציו ולפנים *mechetzio velifnim*, they belong to the
מוצא *motzeh* because the owners have long ago had התייאשו הבעלים *hityayashu
habaalim*. But if the coins are not rusty, then they must be
new. If they are new and found מחציו ולפנים *mechetzio velifnim*, they
belong to the בעל הבית *ba'al habayis*. אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav
Nachman* asks, and we are on the last line of עמוד א
*amud aleph*, even if it is מחציו ולחוץ *mechetzio velachutz*, why should
it belong to the מוצא *motzeh*? It should belong to the בעל
הבית *ba'al habayis* because maybe he is the one who hid it
there for safekeeping. The גמרא *Gemara* will explain that we follow the
majority of people who use that side of the wall.